<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Doug&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://douglascuthbertson.com/tags/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Doug&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>(c) 2015-2024 Douglas Cuthbertson (except where indicated otherwise). The content of this work is licensed under the [Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0), International License](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), again except where indicated otherwise</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 07:43:42 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://douglascuthbertson.com/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Layoffs at F5</title>
      <link>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2023/04/layoffs-at-f5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 07:43:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2023/04/layoffs-at-f5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2023, I was laid of from &lt;a href=&#34;https://f5.com&#34; class=&#34;external-link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;F5, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;. It was a significant layoff of about 9% of the workforce, or 623 employees, worldwide. Given that the economy, at least here in the United States, doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem all that bad, I was surprised to see so many good engineers, product managers, sales people, and others let go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started working for F5 after it acquired Threat Stack on October 1st, 2021. At the time I worked in the Application Infrastructure Protection (AIP) division doing pretty much what I was working on before—adding features to the Windows, Linux, containerized, and Fargate agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not just the layoff that upset me. I really enjoyed working in the Agent Team and particularly on the Windows agent, but now I hear that the company intends to disband AIP, and everything that Threat Stack built over the past decade or so will be gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agents were all well built tools providing telemetry to a backend platform that analyzed events to detect anomalous behavior. Several years ago, an intern and I developed the Windows agent from scratch. The team and I enhanced its capabilities through the years. I thought it had a few clever designs, especially when it came to monitoring activity in the file system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;File system monitoring was accomplished with a quite capable and efficient kernel minifilter. It had a glob pattern-matcher for comparing file activity against a set of rules that defined what behavior was &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo;. Among other things, it could accurately detect file deletions, which is hard to do on NTFS. The minifilter had its own memory allocator and tagged allocations based on what the memory was used for. By running &lt;code&gt;poolmon&lt;/code&gt;, it was easy to determine which components were allocating memory, how much they were allocating, and also ensure that there were no memory leaks at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agent also monitored running processes, associated those processes with the accounts they were running under, watched network connections being established and broken, and looked for significant security-related events. All of this information was relayed to the backend platform for analysis. It was a good system that provided our customers with the situational awareness they needed to mitigate attacks and even stop attacks before a serious incident occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update November 2023&lt;/strong&gt;: Yeesh! F5 had another round of layoffs earlier this month. More of my friends and previous coworkers are now looking for work. It just feels wrong. Yes, there have been a lot of layoffs from much larger tech companies, but they are still raking in lots of money. I suspect F5 is still doing very well, too. They are probably eliminating projects (and thus the employees who were working on them) that don&amp;rsquo;t directly support their core hardware business and (I assume) their aspirations to develop virtual network devices and their own cloud.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Orchard</title>
      <link>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2022/11/the-orchard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 08:07:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2022/11/the-orchard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My wife and I went to the Paramount Theater in Boston last night to see The Orchard, a variation of Anton Chekhov&amp;rsquo;s play, The Cherry Orchard, starring Jessica Hecht and Mikhail Baryshnikov. It was a very avant-garde play. It used a robotic arm that was its own character, a Boston Dynamics robotic dog, and a projection &lt;del&gt;screen&lt;/del&gt; curtain draped in front of the whole stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projection screen was artfully and cinematically used during various scenes to strengthen the presentation of their characters inner emotional state. It also provided atmosphere (through, for example, projecting cherry blossoms blowing in the wind), and acted as an announcer for each act of the play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one real disappointment was that the actors didn&amp;rsquo;t project their voices and enunciate their words well enough, so I found the dialogue difficult to discern through much of the play. I suspect the hope was their microphones and the speakers would be enough to pick up and amplify their voices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pursuit of Happiness Gels in the Imagination</title>
      <link>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2016/03/the-pursuit-of-happiness-gels-in-the-imagination/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://douglascuthbertson.com/2016/03/the-pursuit-of-happiness-gels-in-the-imagination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagination is good, but action needs to be taken in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if the reason I have so many non-fiction books waiting to be read is that I&amp;rsquo;m looking for the thrill of living in a world of fun and self-fulfillment, but I&amp;rsquo;m not willing to create it. I have books on game programming, drawing, sketching, animation, project managment, time management, organizing, clutter reduction, investing and other topics. Even among those I have read, they don&amp;rsquo;t do me much good unless I act upon them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wondermark comic No. 1204, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wondermark.com/c1204/&#34; class=&#34;external-link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Cargo Cult of Adulthood&lt;/a&gt;, started me thinking about imagination versus creating and doing real things. It contrasts buying stuff with buying experiences. The chain of thought starts with buying a movie ticket to get a few hours of being in a dramatized world. Similarly, buying a lottery ticket buys a few days of dreaming there&amp;rsquo;s a chance of becoming a millionaire. The thought continues with the notion that buying stuff can transport us into a fun, but imaginary world. Things like workout clothes, cookbooks, and self-help stuff, says David Malki, the author of Wondermark, are the tickets of admission to the fun imaginary worlds of being fit, eating well and having a good life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He goes on to shortcut the whole process by proposing we skip shopping and just pay someone to give us a daily pep talks about how fun our lives really are, but that&amp;rsquo;s beside the point. These things we buy are just fodder for the imagination unless some action is taken in the real world. Create something new, or clean up something old to make it useful and accessible and then actually put it to use. Put on the workout clothes and exercise. Follow the lessons in that book about sketching, put pencil to paper and practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First efforts will probably stink. Exercising is difficult in the beginning. The first sketch will be awful. It&amp;rsquo;s all about sticking with it. Improvement will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this post is just me giving myself a pep talk (it&amp;rsquo;s ceratinly cheaper than paying someone else to do it), but I have things to do, and I feel more like getting them done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created this blog to become a better writer, quell demons of doubt and to workout ideas. I titled it &amp;ldquo;Dream, Sketch, Code&amp;rdquo;, because I have a lot of half-baked ideas, think about and create software, and I want to get better at sketching and drawing. Besides being a relaxing activity, I&amp;rsquo;d like to draw well enough that I can use sketches to better describe my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
